Guide to the Department of the History of Art, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Department of the History of Art, Yale University, records
1938-2008
RU 796
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
20.5
19 boxes
1326
The records consist of department meeting minutes, course evaluations, student handbooks, notes on the Frick symposium, critiques of the graduate program, and correspondence, memoranda and notes of Henri Focillon and Everett V. Meeks regarding the establishment of the Yale Department of the History of Art. The records also contain the Annals of the Department of History of Art (1950-1991). The annals, a rich source of historical data, include lists and statistics on faculty, students, fellowships, prizes and courses.
Yale University. Department of the History of Art
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 14-B (YRG 14-B), Records of academic departments and programs of the Yale Faculty of Arts and Sciences.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records were transferred from the Department of the History of Art, 1992, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the records is partially restricted. See Collection Contents for details.
Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
Biographical / Historical
The Department of the History of Art was established at Yale in 1940. Its organization and mission were developed by Henri Focillon, a visiting professor from the Sorbonne, at the request of President Charles Seymour. Everette V. Meeks served as the first chair of the department. Organizationally part of the Faculty of Arts and Sciences of Yale College and the Graduate School, the department offers graduate and undergraduate courses.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of department meeting minutes; student handbooks; course evaluations; notes on the Frick symposium; critiques of the graduate program; and correspondence, memoranda and notes of Henri Focillon and Everett V. Meeks regarding the establishment of the Yale Department of the History of Art. The records also contain the Annals of the Department of History of Art (1950-1991). The annals, a rich source of historical data, include lists and statistics on faculty, students, fellowships, prizes and courses.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
Art -- History -- Study and teaching; Universities and colleges -- Administration; Universities and colleges -- Departments; Focillon, Henri, 1881-1943; Meeks, Everett V. (Everett Victor), 1879-1954; Yale University -- Administration; Yale University -- Awards; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University -- Funds and scholarships; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. Department of the History of Art
- Records, 1939-1991; Series I
  - Annals of the Department of History of Art [Compiled by Petrioia S. Hansen], 1950-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 4)
  - Department of History of Art, founding of, 1938-1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Frick Symposium, early phases, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Department meeting minutes, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 7 - 8)
  - Graduate program, critiques of, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Restricted materials
    - Materials removed from the Annals (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Conditions Governing Access
      These records are restricted until 2064.
    - Program applicants, 1939-1941 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Course Evaluations, 1989-2005; Accession 2009-A-006
  - Spring 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Fall 1990 (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
  - Spring 1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fall 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Spring 1991 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Fall 1992 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Spring 1992 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Fall 1993 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - Spring 1993 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
  - Spring 1994 (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
  - Fall 1994 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Fall 1994 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Fall 1995 (Box 3, Folder 24-26)
  - Spring 1995 (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
  - Fall 1996 (Box 3, Folder 29-30)
  - Spring 1996 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Fall 1997 (Box 3, Folder 32-33)
  - Spring 1997 (Box 4, Folder 34-35)
  - Spring 1998 (Box 4, Folder 36-37)
  - Fall 1998 (Box 4, Folder 38-39)
  - Spring 1999 (Box 4, Folder 40-41)
  - Fall 1999 (Box 4, Folder 42-43)
  - Spring 2000 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Spring 2000 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Fall 2000 (Box 5, Folder 46-47)
  - Spring 2001 (Box 5, Folder 48-49)
  - Fall 2001 (Box 5, Folder 50-51)
  - Spring 2002 (Box 5, Folder 52-53)
  - Fall 2002 (Box 5, Folder 54-55)
  - Spring 2003 (Box 5, Folder 56-57)
  - Fall 2003 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Spring 2004 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Fall 2004 (Box 5, Folder 60-61)
  - Spring 2005 (Box 5, Folder 62)
- History of Art Dept. records, 1966-2002; Accession 2009-A-049
  Restricted until January 1, 2078.
  - Levin, Richard: Correspondence, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brodhead, Richard: Corrspondence, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Prown, Jules: Correspondence, 1984-1988 (Box 1, Folder 11-14)
  - Miller and Cahn: Correspondence, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Space Concerns, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Leaves- Faculty, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Report on Space, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Annual Summary Statistics, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Space Function Surveys, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Getty/Muse Project, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Kress Fellowship, 1968-1986 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Kress Fellowship, 1978-1987 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - York St/Chapt St. Building Site Plan Committee, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Prown Report, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Brodhead, Richard: Corrspondence, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Teaching Exhibit, 1968-1987 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - National Gallery Letters, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - CASVA Applications, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Kress Fellowship, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Fellowship Requests, 1993 Fall (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Quid Tum" Dept. Newsletter, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Quid Tum, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Alumni Newsletter, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Newsletter Copies, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - American Arts and Culture Abbot Cummings, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Humanities Publishing Committee, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Griswold, 1976-1986 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - McClendon Kress Grant, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - History of Art Publications, 1962-1978 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Conservation Project, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Alumni Fund, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Faculty Memos, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Prown, Jules: Correspondence, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 75-77)
  - Prown, Jules: Correspondence, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Prown, Jules: Correspondence, 1991 Spring (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Annual Report, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Nordhaus/Lorimer Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Prown, Jules: Correspondence, 1991 Fall (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Faculty Memos, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Mellon Center, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Film, 1974-1982 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Family Educational Right and Privacy, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Development, 1976-1982 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - Clerical Staff HR JobSurveys, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Budget, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Budget, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Space Study, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Chauncey, Henry: Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - Schmidt, Benno: Correspondence, 1989-1992 (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - Lorimer, Linda: Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 110)
  - Arts Space, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 112)
  - Library Alterations, 1974-1991 (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - Audit, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - Leaves of Absence, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 116)
  - Center for American Art, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 117)
  - Leaves of Absence, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 118)
  - Art Gallery Correspondence, 1971-1992 (Box 3, Folder 119)
  - Leaves of Absence, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 120)
  - Leaves of Absence, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 121)
  - Admissions Committee, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 122)
  - Art Gallery Correspondence, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 123)
  - Alumni Fund Correspondence, 1988-1998 (Box 4, Folder 124)
  - History of Art Departamental Review, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - Getty Grant, 1995-1998 (Box 4, Folder 127-130)
  - Getty Grant, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 131)
  - Budget and Acceptance, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 132)
  - Budget, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 133)
  - Budget Notes, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 134)
  - Reorg, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 135)
  - Budget as submitted to Ray Novak, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 136)
  - Budget, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 137)
  - Alumni Fund, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 138)
  - Short List Mod. Jr., 2000 (Box 4, Folder 139)
  - American Search General Info, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 140)
  - Greek Search, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 141)
  - Late 20th Century Art and Art Theory General Correspondence, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 142)
  - Dean's Office: Prior to 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 144)
  - Dean's Office, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 145)
  - Dean's Office, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 146)
  - Grad School Dean Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 4, Folder 147)
  - Budget Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 148)
  - Harcourt Brace, 1963-1966 (Box 4, Folder 149)
  - Griggs Collection, 1967-1977 (Box 4, Folder 150)
  - Crosby/Seymour Library, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 151)
  - Newsletter Extra Copies, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 152)
  - Nov. Newsletter Copies, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 153)
  - Newsletter, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 154)
  - Newsletter Copies, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 155)
  - Penney, Sherry: Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 156)
  - Budget, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 157)
  - Budget, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 158)
  - Budget, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 159)
  - Sr App't, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 160)
  - Morse Fellowships, 1961-1989 (Box 5, Folder 161)
  - Leaves of Absence, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 162)
  - Leaves of Absence, 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 163)
  - Leaves of Absence, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 164)
  - Leaves of Absence, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 165)
  - Mellon Center - general, 1970-1977 (Box 5, Folder 166)
  - GESO, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 167)
  - Frame Symposium, 1994 November (Box 5, Folder 168)
  - BAC Summer Intern Fellowship, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 169)
  - BAC Yale Summer Program, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 170)
  - Budget, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 171)
  - Annual Report, 1989-1990 (Box 5, Folder 172)
  - Annual Report, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 173)
  - Annual Report, 1991-1992 (Box 5, Folder 174)
  - Annual Report, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 175)
  - Annual Report, 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 176)
  - Annual Report, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 177)
  - Annual Report, 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 178)
  - Annual Report, 1996-1997 (Box 5, Folder 179)
  - Responses to Annual Faculty Activity Report, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 180)
  - Annual Report, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 181)
  - Annual Report, 1974-1981 (Box 5, Folder 182)
  - Annual Report, 1983-1984 (Box 5, Folder 183)
  - Annual Report, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 184)
  - Annual Report, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 185)
  - Annual Report, 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 186)
- Personnel files, 1973-2007; Accession 2009-A-050
  Restricted until January 1, 2085.
  - Regis Michel, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Miscallaneous Applications, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Wheelwright Memorial, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Art Lecture: Nan Swid, Addie Powell, 2008 April 15; Accession 2009-A-103 (Box 1)
  The materials are open for research.
  Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
  - Art Lecture: Nan Swid, Addie Powell, 2008 April 15; computer files (DVD-Video)
    General note
    Contact Public Services (phone: 203 432-1735, e-mail: mssa.reference@yale.edu) for information on accessing this digital object.
    - Use copy, optical disc (DVD) (Box 1U)